Guide to the Frederick Charles Barghoorn Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frederick Charles Barghoorn papers
1938-1988
MS 1676
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.5
The bulk of the material is from the 1960s and early 1970s, and includes correspondence, departmental and organizational files, research files, and publications. There is little mention of Barghoorn's arrest by the Soviet government in 1963, except for a brief summary of the incident in a letter to Pat Briggs dated November 10, 1965.
Barghoorn, Frederick Charles, 1911-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Steven Barghoorn, 1994.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research, with the exception of restricted files relating to faculty searches and student recommendations. These records will be open January 1, 2060.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series: I. Yale University Files, 1953-1979, II. Professional Files, 1957-1988, III. Subject Files, 1939-1988.
Biographical / Historical
Frederick Charles Barghoorn was born in New York City in 1911. He received his undergraduate degree from Amherst College in 1934 and his doctorate in history from Harvard in 1941. In the 1940s, Barghoorn served in the Division of East European Affairs in the State Department and in the press section of the U.S. Embassy in Moscow. From 1949 to 1951, he headed a federal project interviewing Soviet defectors to analyze their government and society. From 1947 until his retirement in 1980, Barghoorn was a professor in Yale's political science department. He also taught at the University of Chicago and Columbia University. In 1963, Soviet officials jailed Barghoorn in Moscow on espionage charges and released him only under pressure from President John F. Kennedy. Frederick Barghoorn died in Woodbridge, Connecticut, in 1991.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the material is from the 1960s and early 1970s, and includes correspondence, departmental and organizational files, research files, and publications. There is little mention of Barghoorn's arrest by the Soviet government in 1963, except for a brief summary of the incident in a letter to Pat Briggs dated November 10, 1965.
College teachers -- United States; Communism -- Soviet Union -- History; Dissenters -- Soviet Union; Education, Higher -- United States; Nationalism -- Soviet Union; Opposition (Political science); Political science -- Study and teaching; Political scientists -- United States; Propaganda, Communist -- Soviet Union; Propaganda, Soviet; Sovietologists -- United States; Teachers -- United States; Totalitarianism; Universities and colleges -- United States -- Administration; Europe, Eastern -- Study and teaching; Soviet Union -- Economic policy; Soviet Union -- Foreign relations; Soviet Union -- Intellectual life; Soviet Union -- Politics and government; Soviet Union -- Study and teaching; Barghoorn, Frederick Charles, 1911-; Lane, Robert Edwards; Mickiewicz, Ellen Propper; Yale University. Department of Political Science
- Yale University Files, 1953-1979; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Yale University Files (0.5 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically and relate to Yale's Political Science, and Russian and East European Studies departments. The files concern departmental and university business, and include correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports, and memoranda. The files also include Barghoorn's syllabi, reading lists, and examinations for the classes he taught at Yale. Restricted material relating to faculty searches and student recommendations is listed at the end of the inventory.
  - Political Science Department
    - General, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Advanced Political Studies, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Annual reports [by Barghoorn], 1954-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Courses
    - Political Science 32b, 1969-1970,1972,1975 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    - Political Science 66a and Political Science 66b, 1953-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
    - Political Science 118b, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Political Science 118b and Political Science 177a, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Political Science 159b, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Political Science 176b, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Political Science 177a, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Political Science 365a, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Political Science 770a, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Political Science 771b, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Political Science 776b, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Faculty searches
    General note
    See: Restricted Files, Box 8, Folders 1-8. Material will be open January 1, 2060.
  - Kaufman, Herbert, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    General
    Department chair; mostly outgoing correspondence, Barghoorn to Kaufman.
  - Lane, Robert E., 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Department chair; memos to the faculty and correspondence with Barghoorn.
  - Russian and East European Studies, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Russian Seminar [report], 1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Student evaluations and recommendations
    See:Restricted Files, Box 8, Folders 9-13. Material will be open January 1, 2060.
- Professional Files, 1957-1988; Series II
  Barghoorn's Professional Files (1.5 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically and include correspondence; materials on grants and funding agencies; various professional organizations and conferences files; and writings, including book reviews and book chapters. The correspondence is divided into several chronological sections. Within each section letters are arranged alphabetically by the last name of Barghoorn's correspondent. There is also a folder of the correspondence between Barghoorn and his former student, Ellen Mickiewicz. The bulk of the correspondence consists of outgoing letters from Barghoorn, chiefly to professional colleagues in academia and government, discussing his and others' work in Soviet studies. There is little mention of his arrest by the Soviet government in 1963, except for a brief summary of the incident in a letter to Pat Briggs dated 1965 November 10. Other letters concern collaborative projects, funding opportunities, and departmental and university matters. A few items mention student unrest at Yale in the spring of 1970.
  Grants and funding files contain correspondence, proposals, and application materials. Professional organizations and conferences files include correspondence, programs, and drafts of papers. Barghoorn's writings are comprised of book reviews and chapters for Robert Dahl's Regimes and Oppositions and Wendell Bell and Walter E. Freeman's Ethnicity and Nation-building.
  - Bibliographies and curricula vita, 1957-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    Materials are arranged alphabetically within each date span.
    - 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
    - 1965-1975
      - A-H (Box 2, Folder 6-13)
      - I-Z (Box 3, Folder 14-25)
    - 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - 1979-1988 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Mickiewicz, Ellen (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Grants and funding
    - American Council of Learned Societies, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - American Philosophical Society, 1966-1972 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Ford Foundation, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Guggenheim Foundation, 1872 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Hazen Foundation, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - RELM Foundation, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - United States Information Agency, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Professional associations and conferences
    - American Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - American Political Science Association, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Conference on Dissent in the Soviet Union, McMaster Studies, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - International Committee for Soviet and East European Studies, Garmisch Conference, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - International Studies Association, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Writings
    - Book reviews by Barghoorn, 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Ethnicity and Nation-building [book chapter], 1971 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Regimes and Oppositions [book chapter], 1965-1970 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous [invitations and fliers], Circa 1980-1986 (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Subject Files, 1939-1988; Series III
  Barghoorn's Subject Files (1.5 linear feet) are mostly from the 1940s and 1950s and primarily concern the history, politics, and cultural life of the Soviet Union and its republics. There are both English and Russian-language articles, clippings, publications, and Barghoorn's handwritten and typed notes. Many of the items have been annotated by Barghoorn and others.
  - Notes and draft, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Publications, Circa 1958-1988 (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
  - Publications, Circa 1958-1988 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Soviet republics
    - Karelo-Finnish Republic, Circa 1949 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Kirghizistan, 1939-1959 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Moldavia, 1956-1959 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Mongolia, 1955-1960 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Turkistan, 1945-1955 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Ukraine, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Soviet Union
    - Drama and cinema, 1944-1949 (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
    - Ethnic composition in Party, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Freedom of expression, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Geographic patriotism, 1945-1957 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Intelligentsia, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Nationalities and representation in the Presidium, C. C. and other control agencies, 1957-1959 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Persecution of non-Russian intelligentsia, 1946-1954 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Politics in the USSR, Circa 1986 (Box 7, Folder 24-25)
    - Popular forces, 1954, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Progress and nationalism, 1946-1951 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Russian church and patriotism, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Russification, successes and failures, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 29)
- Restricted Files
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until January 1, 2060.
  - University Files, 1963-1987; 1
    - Political Science Department
      - Faculty Searches
        - Comparative Communism, 1966-1969
          - General (Box 8, Folder 1)
          - Candidates (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
        - Concilium Chair, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 4)
        - Eastern Europe, 1965-1967
          - General (Box 8, Folder 5)
          - Candidates (Box 8, Folder 6-8)
  - Student evaluations and recommendations, 1961-1984 (Box 8, Folder 9-13)